Host: Estela de Carlotto!
(Applause)
Dearest friends,
thank you for welcoming me
in the name of all "Abuelas
de Plaza de Mayo"; I'm just one of them.
And my story is the same
as my fellow women:
we got together deeply pained,
not knowing what to do,
lacking information, surrounded by danger,
and leaving everything behind.
I was a school principal but I retired
to search for a Disappeared loved one,
a child of mine, a daughter,
but it was a double search
because my daughter
was expecting a baby.
At my age, I was born in the 1930s,
dictatorships were part of my education,
but I never thought
that the last civic-military dictatorship
would bring such a horrifying
and sinister a project.
I had to educate myself about it,
I had to learn about it and to understand,
but we did something wonderful
which allowed us to keep on fighting:
we joined together.
Even if we stood alone, when we saw
there were other mothers out there,
with same faces and feeling the same pain,
we dared to ask what their stories were
and so we decided
to search for answers together.
This is how this group took shape
37 years ago.
And we are still getting together
- the ones who have survived -
because many of us passed away,
and others are ill.
We have different ideologies now,
a different culture or religion,
but there is still something
that unites us,
that common thread of pain,
that fight that never ends,
because I believe not a day goes by
that a mother doesn't love
her sons or daughters,
especially if she has been searching
for her beloved son.
So we started by
getting together and searching
not knowing exactly where or how to do it.
We started searching for the babies
at first, but we got no answers.
They were never brought back to us.
We prepared our homes and the layettes,
but we soon left our families uncared for,
we swept our traditional gender roles
as mothers, as wives,
in my case my job as a teacher too,
and let our husbands
take care of the home;
that's what we tell people who asked us
how were the grandfathers involved.
Well, they were there,
fulfilling domestic duties.
I think of them as anonymous heroes
because they were left to care
for the children at home,
provide as sole breadwinners,
and wait for us in silence
because every time we went marching
they never knew if we were to come back.
I remember one time
I was a little discouraged
and said that I'd quit
with no apparent reason,
and my husband intervened and told me
that I couldn't, I had to go on,
because the Grandmothers needed me.
It was the only time I felt like quitting,
but never again; on the contrary.
You know that I found my grandson,
we were reunited, we're living together!
(Applause)
What a moment!
But I want to let you know, to share
it with you: I didn't find him by myself.
I've got help from the Grandmothers,
from all of you, all this time
- the longest period in the history
of democracy here in Argentina -
because we got together
in a common understanding
the dictatorship's affected all of us,
and we must ensure it doesn't happen again
and that we must find and get back
our kidnapped Disappeared alive.
So my grandson is everybody's grandson.
See, something amazing happened:
there is a permanent smile on people's
faces in the country since that encounter.
It may be because of this woman's fight
for 37 years, out of love,
overcoming hatred and resentment,
hoping this doesn't happen again,
that our children will live
to be free, to be freethinkers,
and to learn how to disagree
but live together as brothers.
That's why I think
this multitudinous, wonderful event
we're attending in this cultural space
should foster coexistence
beyond differences.
The Grandmothers,
even today argue on things,
we have diverging views we don't agree on,
but when we have to come to a decision
we are resolving it together.
We know we are lucky,
but I sometimes say is funny
how one gets to thank life through pain.
For my daughter gave her life
knowing that things should change,
and they are,
but there are many roads left unexplored.
One of them is science.
There is no other genetic Data Bank
anywhere in the whole world but here
where grandparents can search
for their kidnapped grandchildren.
We are the only country with a history
in the search
of stolen babies, now adults.
But what a joyous moment
when we are reunited!
The happiness!
I feel younger, I feel better.
Sometimes I feel like throwing this cane,
but I have to tell you that is a symbol
of all the Grandmothers,
because we never kneel down,
we are always marching head-high,
resolutely, determined and with dignity.
Because there is no need for violence
in order to have justice done.
Justice is being done.
And I think we made a small contribution
to our current democracy
that we hope it will last forever.
(Applause)
In this brief talk
I wish you all the best.
If you are here, then I think
it's because you are those Argentineans
who deserve respect, to be heard,
and have their demands satisfied.
The most important thing
is not to be alone, not to give up.
Because perseverance
is the key of all triumphs.
37 years later I am here,
and I thank you today
for helping me find my grandson;
it's something worth fighting for.
Thank you very much.
(Applause)